<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Juampi&#039;s Blog</title>
    <link href="https://barreto.jp/blog" />
    <link type="application/atom+xml" rel="self" href="https://barreto.jp/blog/feed.atom/" />
    <updated>2022-12-01T09:14:41+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://barreto.jp/blog/feed.atom/</id>
    <author>
        <name>Juan Pablo Barreto</name>
    </author>
                <entry>
    <id>https://barreto.jp/blog/interviewing-conflict/</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://barreto.jp/blog/interviewing-conflict/" />
    <title>Interviewing Conflict</title>
    <published>2022-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2022-11-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Juan Pablo Barreto</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">It is very common to start a technical interview by giving a coding challenge to the candidate and observing their problem-solving skills. Although technical skills are important, most developers face many soft-skill problems on a daily basis.</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <h2>Intro</h2>

<p>It is very common to start a technical interview by giving a coding challenge to the candidate and observing their problem-solving skills.</p>

<p>Although technical skills are important, most developers face many soft-skill problems on a daily basis. From reviewing pull requests to making RFCs, developers have to exchange ideas, negotiate, and deal with opinions from different cultures.</p>

<p>It is the aim of this article to present interview strategies that can be used to detect conflicting candidates before hiring them.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/2-interviewing-conflict.jpg" alt="Interviewing Conflict Preview" />
Photo by <a href="https://unsplash.com/@hungriadb" target="_blank">Diogo Hungria</a> on Unsplash</p>

<h2>The price of pride</h2>

<p>Developers with experience tend to have big egos.
Pride can make people focus on who is right or wrong, instead of working on what is right for the codebase.
These long discussions tend to be very exhausting for everyone involved, lowering the morale of the developers involved, and preventing them from ever arguing with them again.</p>

<h2>Interviewing for Conflicts</h2>

<p>Would it be helpful to be able to identify candidates who will not integrate well with the rest of the team during the interview process?</p>

<p><a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=interviewing+conflict" target="_blank">It is common practice</a> in the interview process to explicitly ask the candidate how would they deal with conflict. They are usually asked to describe a situation where they had conflicts with a colleague, and how did they manage to solve the problem. Although the intention is good, this is a theoretical question, and the practice can be far from ideal.</p>

<p>A practice I adopted while interviewing is to focus on generating controlled conflicts and observing how the candidate reacts. Are they immediately defensive or are they considering new ideas? Are they asking questions to understand it better, or are they fixed in their initial solution? Can they recognize the pain points in their solution? Can they comprehend the tradeoffs from both solutions and make an informed decision considering both ideas?</p>

<p>This practice is otherwise known as <a href="https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/devil%27s_advocate#Noun" target="_blank">devil’s advocate</a>, and it is not only useful to test the strength of a proposal, but also to test how someone reacts to a difference of opinion from their own.</p>

<h2>Do it yourself</h2>

<p>This technique works only if you are going against an idea of their own. It helps if previous to the interview you reviewed a take-home test. Before the interview, we look for opinionated decisions that might have trade-offs with other approaches: are they using a specific pattern? Are they separating their responsibilities correctly? Could they be more decoupled?</p>

<p>Once you’ve recognized these potential points, you should formulate a question that challenges the candidate to find weaknesses in them. You can achieve this by pointing out an edge case or proposing hypothetical scenarios where the solution doesn’t scale correctly.</p>

<p>You should show that you don’t agree with their implementation, but instead of saying why you don’t, you should describe a situation that illustrates its flaws.</p>

<p>The exercise is for them to reflect on their solution, understand the weakness you describe, and propose an alternative that will contemplate both, even if they don’t fully agree. Here, the goal is to get them to analyze the trade-offs of both solutions and engage in a productive discussion.</p>

<p>It sounds simple, but you would be surprised at how many people act defensively against their code and have a hard time letting go of their own implementation.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Overall, what makes a high-performing team is not only having superhero developers, but having a healthy dynamic between team members.</p>

<p>Team members who can communicate ideas without getting personal and collaborate towards a greater codebase will prove more valuable in the long run.</p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>https://barreto.jp/blog/seo-testing/</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="https://barreto.jp/blog/seo-testing/" />
    <title>Testing your SEO with PHP &amp; Pest</title>
    <published>2022-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2022-09-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Juan Pablo Barreto</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">Just like any other test suite, SEO tests will give your team confidence in your HTML structure and will prevent expensive mistakes.</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>SEO testing is a practice that can prevent unwanted changes in search engines.
If you are interested in knowing why, in this <a href="https://medium.com/studocu-techblog/the-importance-of-testing-your-seo-9056e8f47ef7" target="_blank">medium article</a> I explain the importance of it, and the possible consequences of not doing so.</p>

<p>This article will focus on testing a PHP project using the utility package <a href="https://github.com/juampi92/test-seo" target="_blank">test-seo</a>.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Note: The examples in this post are made using <a href="https://pestphp.com/" target="_blank">Pest</a> with Laravel, but none of these are required for the package to work.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><img src="/assets/images/1-test-seo-code-preview.jpg" alt="TestSEO Code Preview" /></p>

<h2>Setup</h2>

<p>To install the package, run:</p>

<pre><code class="language-bash">composer require juampi92/test-seo --dev
</code></pre>

<blockquote>
  <p>It is assumed PHPUnit and Pest are already installed in your project.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2>Testing the landing page</h2>

<p>The first step to a successful landing page, is a 200 status code, so we'll start with that.</p>

<pre><code class="language-php">test('landing page SEO tags', function () {
    $response = get('/')-&gt;assertStatus(200);
});
</code></pre>

<p>To use this package, you will have to instantiate the TestSEO using the HTML response:</p>

<pre><code class="language-php">test('landing page SEO tags', function () {
    $response = get('/')-&gt;assertStatus(200);

    // And now we generate the TestSEO object with the html response:
    $seo = new TestSEO($response-&gt;getContent());
});
</code></pre>

<p>For the landing page, we would like to test that the title is <code>My Blog</code>, the canonical url is self-referencing, and the robots are correct.</p>

<pre><code class="language-php">test('landing page SEO tags', function () {
    // ...
    $seo = new TestSEO($response-&gt;getContent());

    expect($seo-&gt;data)
        -&gt;title()-&gt;toBe('My Blog')
        -&gt;canonical()-&gt;toEqual(route('home'))
        -&gt;robots()-&gt;index()-&gt;toBeTrue()
        -&gt;robots()-&gt;follow()-&gt;toBeTrue();
});
</code></pre>

<h2>Snapshot testing</h2>

<p>To do snapshot testing, first we need to install spatie's snapshot package:</p>

<pre><code class="language-bash">composer require spatie/pest-plugin-snapshots --dev
</code></pre>

<p>Now we only have to assert that the TestSEO matches the snapshot.</p>

<pre><code class="language-php">use function Spatie\Snapshots\{assertMatchesJsonSnapshot};

test('landing page SEO tags', function () {
    // ...
    $seo = new TestSEO($response-&gt;getContent());

    assertMatchesJsonSnapshot(json_encode($seo));
});
</code></pre>

<p>The TestSEO implements the <a href="https://www.php.net/manual/en/jsonserializable.jsonserialize.php" target="_blank">jsonSerialize()</a> method to be compared against the JSON snapshot.</p>

<p>By default, it will use a simple structure serializer that includes the title, description, robots, etc. If you would like to make your custom Serializer, you can follow the following steps:</p>

<pre><code class="language-php">use Juampi92\TestSEO\SEOData;
use Juampi92\TestSEO\SnapshotFormatters\SnapshotSerializer;

class MySerializer implements SnapshotSerializer
{
    public function toArray(SEOData $data): array
    {
        return [
            'title' =&gt; $data-&gt;title(),
            'description' =&gt; $data-&gt;description(),
            'robots' =&gt; (string) $data-&gt;robots(),
            'canonical' =&gt; $data-&gt;canonical(),
            'pagination' =&gt; [
                'prev' =&gt; $data-&gt;prev(),
                'next' =&gt; $data-&gt;next(),
            ],
        ];
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>To use this formatter, you simply have to pass it as TestSEO's second parameter:</p>

<pre><code class="language-php">test('landing page SEO tags', function () {
    // ...
    $seo = new TestSEO($response-&gt;getContent(), new MySerializer());

    $json = json_encode($seo);
});
</code></pre>

<h3>What about seeded data?</h3>

<p>When testing dynamic pages, you will have to seed data in order to test the page. Seeded data usually uses random attributes which will make every seed unique. Generating unique attributes each time will never match the previous attribute stored in the snapshot.</p>

<p><strong>How do we solve this problem?</strong> We don't fake.</p>

<p>When testing SEO pages, we will control our attributes. If we want to test how a title gets cropped in the <code>&lt;title/&gt;</code> tag, we will seed always the same long title.</p>

<pre><code class="language-php">test('article page SEO tags', function () {
    $article = Article::factory()-&gt;create([
        'title' =&gt; 'This is a very long title, and I would like to see it cropped',
    ]);

    $response = get(RouteHelper::article($article))-&gt;assertStatus(200);
    $seo = new TestSEO($response-&gt;getContent(), new MySerializer());

    expect($seo-&gt;data)
        -&gt;title()-&gt;toBe('This is a very long title, and I would like to see it... - My Blog');

    $json = json_encode($seo);
    // {
    //    "title": "This is a very long title, and I would like to see it... - My Blog",
    //    ...
    // }
});
</code></pre>

<p>Now we have a new issue: unique IDs. It is very likely that you will get different IDs on each run, and if you use IDs in URLs, the snapshots won't match.</p>

<p>The easiest solution to his problem is to replace the unique IDs with a generic placeholder, and that's what the default serializer is doing.</p>

<pre><code class="language-bash">/article/this-is-a-very-long-title/15
</code></pre>

<p>Gets replaced to:</p>

<pre><code class="language-bash">/article/this-is-a-very-long-title/{id}
</code></pre>

<p>Now, any seeded article will match the snapshot.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In the case where replacing numbers for {id} is not sufficient, snapshot testing may not be the best approach.</p>
</blockquote>

<h2>Most common assertions</h2>

<p>Search engines have made it clear that breaking certain rules can lead to a negative ranking.
In order to test them easier, this package includes assertions for some of these rules:</p>

<h3>Never have more than one H1</h3>

<p>Search engines pay a lot of attention to the H1, and that's also why they do not like it when you use more than one per page.
This package comes with a method:</p>

<pre><code class="language-php">$seo-&gt;assertThereIsOnlyOneH1();
</code></pre>

<h3>All images have <code>alt</code> attribute</h3>

<p>This is also a good SEO practice: Images should have an "alternative" tag with a meaningful text.</p>

<pre><code class="language-php">$seo-&gt;assertAllImagesHaveAltText();
</code></pre>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>If your website relies on search engines, you will do whatever you can to please them, and that includes not messing up.
Having a decent SEO coverage can give your team the confidence to refactor pages and now worry about modifying the SEO structure by accident.</p>

<p>Checkout the package to see all its features, and Pull-Request are welcome!</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/juampi92/test-seo#test-seo" target="_blank">https://github.com/juampi92/test-seo</a></p>
    ]]></content>
</entry>
    </feed>
